A Finding Aid to the Gene Davis Papers, 1920-2000, bulk 1942-1990, in the Archives of American Art AAA.davigene
Archives of American Art
Gene Davis papers
bulk 1942-1990
1920-2000
AAA.davigene
Archives of American Art
16 Linear feet
The papers of the artist Gene Davis measure 16 linear feet and date from 1920-2000, with the bulk of materials dating from 1942-1990. Papers document Davis’s personal life and his career as an artist and educator, as well as his career as a journalist in the 1940s and 1950s, through biographical materials, correspondence, interviews, business records, estate records, writings by and about Gene Davis, printed materials concerning Davis’s art career, personal and art-related photographs, and artwork by Davis and others.
Davis, Gene, 1920-1985
Existence and Location of Copies note
Some of the moving image and sound recordings in this collection have been digitized for research access and are available in the Archives of American Art offices.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical/Historical note
Gene Davis (1920-1985) was a Washington, D.C.-based artist and educator who worked in a variety of media, including painting, drawing, collage, video, light sculpture, and conceptual art. Davis is best known for his vertical stripe paintings and his association with the Washington Color School.
Davis was born in 1920 in Washington, D.C. and began his career as a writer. In his twenties he wrote pulp stories and worked as a journalist, reporting for United Press International and serving as a White House correspondent for Transradio Press Service during the Truman administration. Later, he worked in public relations for the Automobile Association of America. A self-taught artist, Davis began painting while still working full-time as a writer, influenced by the prevailing abstract expressionist artists of the time, his frequent visits to the Corcoran Gallery and Phillips Collection in Washington, D.C., and by his friend and mentor, Jacob Kainen. His first one-man show was held in the lobby of the Dupont Theater in Washington in 1952. He had a drawing accepted in the Corcoran Area Show in 1953, and won several local art prizes in the 1950s. He began showing work regularly in galleries around Washington, such as the Watkins Gallery at American University, the Gres Gallery, and the Henri Gallery, and had solo exhibitions at Jefferson Place Gallery in 1959 and 1961. Many of the painters who made up what became known as the Washington Color School also showed there, including Kenneth Noland, Howard Mehring, and Sam Gilliam. In 1965, the Washington Gallery of Modern Art held a seminal exhibition entitled Washington Color Painters, which included Davis, Noland, Mehring, Morris Louis, Thomas Downing, and Paul Reed.
Davis began showing outside of Washington regularly in the 1960s, including the Poindexter and Fischbach galleries in New York City, and in several important group shows at museums such as the Museum of Modern Art, the Whitney Museum, and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art. He had three works shown in the 1964 exhibition Post-Painterly Abstraction, organized by the influential art critic Clement Greenberg at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art. In the late 1960s, he began teaching art classes at the Corcoran School, and spent the summer of 1969 as artist in residence at Skidmore College’s “Summer in Experiment” program.
Davis experimented with form continuously throughout his career, including a period of conceptual work in the late 1960s. In 1969 he participated in the “Giveaway,” organized by Douglas Davis and Ed McGowin, in which multiple copies of a Davis painting were given away to invited guests in a gesture intended to subvert the art market. Davis also began experimenting with scale, creating a series of tiny paintings he called "Micro-paintings," which were exhibited at Fischbach Gallery in 1968. Around this time he also began working with film and video, recruiting models from his art classes to enact tightly choreographed movement pieces that played with rhythm and interval. Convinced by a lawyer that his videos were a liability without having obtained releases from the models, Davis destroyed all but one of his video works. The surviving video, “Video Puzzle,” shows a foreshortened view of a model on the floor of a gallery spelling out a statement by Clement Greenberg at predetermined intervals.
Davis made several large-scale site-specific works using the stripe motif in public places. The first of these was created in the Bal Harbour, Florida, Neiman Marcus department store in 1970. Later works included Franklin’s Footpath, executed in the road leading to the Philadelphia Museum of Art in 1972, and Niagara (1979) at ArtPark in Lewistown, NY, promoted at the time as the largest painting in the world. Interior large-scale works were created twice at the Corcoran Gallery, with Magic Circle (1975) and Ferris Wheel (1982), both executed in the museum’s rotunda. Black Yo-Yo was created for the Cranbrook Academy in 1980, and Sun Sonata (1983), an illuminated wall of colored liquid-filled tubes, was created as an architectural feature of the Muscarelle Museum of Art in Williamsburg, Virginia. Plans for an unexecuted work called "Grass Painting," for a site near the Kennedy Center in Washington, D.C., were exhibited in the 1974 "Art Now" festival.
In the late 1970s and 1980s Davis consistently exhibited his work in several solo gallery shows a year, and also had numerous solo exhibitions in major museums. A major exhibition, Recent Paintings, was organized by the Walker Art Center in 1978, and traveled to the Corcoran Gallery of Art in 1979. A drawing retrospective was held at the Brooklyn Museum of art in 1983, and the same year the Washington Project for the Arts organized an exhibition entitled Child and Man: A Collaboration, featuring drawings Davis made in response to childrens' drawings. Davis died suddenly in April 1985 at the age of 65, and a major retrospective of his work was held at the Smithsonian National Museum of American Art in 1987.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Gene Davis conducted by Estill Curtis Pennington on April 23, 1981. A transcript is available on the Archives of American Art website.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of the artist Gene Davis measure 16 linear feet and date from 1920-2000, with the bulk of materials dating from 1942-1990. Papers document Davis’s personal life and his career as an artist and educator, and to a lesser degree his early career as a journalist in the 1940s and 1950s, through biographical materials, correspondence, interviews, business records, estate records, writings by and about Gene Davis, printed materials concerning Davis’s art career, personal and art-related photographs, and artwork by Davis and others.
Biographical materials include birth and death certificates, awards, biographical narratives by Gene Davis and others, CVs, résumés, personal documents from Davis's family and childhood, documents related to his work as a White House correspondent, documentation related to his death and memorial service, and papers for the family pets. A video documentary about Davis by Carl Colby is found on one videocassette.
Correspondence is mainly of a professional nature, and correspondents include gallery and museum curators, private art collectors, publishers, fellow artists, art educators, academics, and students. Letters document exhibitions, sales, book projects, teaching jobs, visits to studios, local art community events in the Washington, D.C. area, and other projects. Significant correspondents include Gene Baro, Douglas Davis, Clement Greenberg, Gerald Nordland, William Seitz, Alma Thomas, and Donald Wall. Interviews and lectures include sound recordings and transcripts. Many of the interviews were broadcast or published. Also found is a single lecture by Davis given in 1969 at the National Collection of Fine Arts, Smithsonian Institution, entitled “Contemporary Painting.” Sound recordings are found for three of the interviews and for the lecture, on 4 sound reels and 1 sound cassette.
Business records include artwork documentation, price lists, sales records, contracts, financial and legal records, gallery and museum files documenting sales and exhibitions, records related to the construction of Davis’s home studio in 1970, and a few teaching records. Estate records mainly reflect Florence Davis’s efforts to document the works of her husband, and to manage their exhibition, promotion, and sale after his death in April 1985. Estate records include an inventory of artworks, documentation of gifts to museums, correspondence, legal, and financial records. Writings include notes, drafts of essays, artist statements, and articles by Davis, and many articles by others about Davis. Several of Davis’s articles reflect specifically on the Washington, D.C. art scene. Also found are drafts of monographs on Davis including one by Donald Wall (1975) and one by Steven Naifeh (1982). Records of Naifeh’s book also include photographs of all black and white and color plates from the published book. Among the writings are also notes and research files of Percy North, who worked on an update to Naifeh’s 1982 bibliography after Davis’s death.
Printed materials include annual reports of museums, published arts-related calendars, auction catalogs, brochures from organizations with which Davis had some affiliation, exhibition announcements and invitations, exhibition catalogs, magazine articles, newspaper clippings, newsletters, posters, press releases, and other published material. Photographs include personal photographs of Gene and Florence Davis and their families, portraits of Gene Davis, photographs of Gene Davis with artworks and working in the studio, Davis’ art classes and students, installations of site-specific works, conceptual and video works, exhibition openings, and photographs of artwork, both installed in exhibitions and individually photographed. Found among the photographs are also four videocassettes documenting the Gene Davis retrospective as installed at the Smithsonian National Museum of American Art in 1987.
Artwork includes photographs, drawings, moving images, and documentation of conceptual art. Works by Davis include documentation of the 1969 “Giveaway” with Douglas Davis and Ed McGowin, “The Artist’s Fingerprints Except for One which belongs to someone else,” documentation of his “Air Displacement” happening, a short film entitled “Patricia,” and a video entitled “Video Puzzle.” Other moving images include four reels of film of Davis’s stripe paintings, and other experiments with motion picture film and photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated 1981 by Gene Davis and 1986 by his wife, Florence. Additional material donated 1991 and 1993 from Smithsonian American Art Museum via a bequest to them from the Gene and Florence Davis estate. Much of the 1993 addition was assembled by art historian Percy North at the request of Florence Davis. An additional folder of photographs of Davis taken in 1969 but printed in 2000 was later added to the collection.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1930-1987 (0.6 linear feet; Boxes 1, 17)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1943-1990 (1.7 linear feet; Boxes 1-3)
Series 3: Interviews and Lectures, 1964-1983 (0.3 linear feet; Box 3)
Series 4: Business and Estate Records, 1942-1990 (1.6 linear feet; Boxes 3-5, 17, OV 20)
Series 5: Writings, 1944-1990 (2 linear feet; Boxes 5-6, 17, OV 19)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1942-1990 (5.2 linear feet; Boxes 7-11, 17-18, OV 20)
Series 7: Photographs, 1920-2000 (3.8 linear feet; Boxes 11-15, 17, OV 19)
Series 8: Artwork, 1930-1985 (0.8 linear feet; Boxes 15-16, 18)
Baro, Gene; Colby, Carl; Davis, Douglas; Davis, Florence; Greenberg, Clement, 1909-1994; McGowin, Ed, 1938-; Naifeh, Steven, 1952-; Nordland, Gerald; North, Percy, 1945-; Seitz, William Chapin; Thomas, Alma; Wall, Donald; White House (Washington, D.C.).; Art--Study and teaching; Artists' studios--Photographs; Collagists--Washington, D.C; Color-field painting--Washington (D.C.); Conceptual artists--Washington, D.C; Interviews; Painters--Washington (D.C.); Painting, Modern--20th century--Washington (D.C.); Photographs; Reporters and reporting--Washington (D.C.); Sound recordings; Transcripts; Video artists--Washington, D.C.; Video recordings
- Biographical Material, 1930-1987; Series 1; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1, 17
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains biographical documents such as birth and death certificates, awards, biographical narratives by Gene Davis and others, CVs, and résumés. Also found are personal documents from Gene Davis's family and childhood, documentation related to his death and memorial service, and papers for the family pets. Juvenilia includes a childhood essay and drawing, and memorabilia includes performance programs from the 1930s, French currency from 1944, and a clipping annotated by his mother. Papers related to Davis's job as a White House correspondent include schedules, invitations, telephone directories, and documentation of President Truman's travels.
  Documentation of Davis's death and memorials include programs and typescript of remarks made at the service, a sound recording of the service on one sound cassette, photocopies of published obituaries, and a photograph album created for the memorial.
  Arrangement note
  Additional material related to Davis's years as a journalist is found in series 5, Writings and series 7, Photographs. Original copies of many of the published obituaries are found in series 6, Printed Material. Additional photographs from Davis's childhood and early years are found in series 7, Photographs.
  - Biographical Narratives, circa 1963-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birth and Death Certificates, 1969; 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificates and Awards, 1953 - circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - CVs and Résumés, circa 1968-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Documentary Gene Davis by Carl Colby, 1986; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Broadcast on WETA-TV (Washington, D.C.)
  - Dog Papers, 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Family Papers, 1939-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - High School Yearbook, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Horoscope, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Juvenilia, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Memorabilia, 1937-1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memorial Service Program and Remarks, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorial Service, Sound Recording, 1985; 2 Sound cassettes duplicates; 1 Sound cassettes original (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorial Events and Proclamations, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Obituaries, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Papers Related to White House Correspondent Job, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photograph Album for Memorial, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Oversized album housed in Box 17
  - Oversized Photograph Album from Box 1, folder 16 (Box 17)
- Correspondence, 1943-1990; Series 2; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-3, OV 19
  Correspondence is mainly of a professional nature, and correspondents include gallery and museum curators, private art collectors, publishers, fellow artists, art educators, academics, and students. Letters document exhibitions, sales, book projects, teaching jobs, visits to studios, local art community events in the Washington, D.C. area, and other projects. A few early letters are found related to Davis's personal life and work as a journalist prior to 1955, but most correspondence is from after that date and pertains to his art career. Almost all letters are addressed to Gene Davis, but scattered letters, including letters of condolence from 1985, are addressed to Florence Davis. Significant correspondents include Gene Baro, Douglas Davis, Clement Greenberg, Gerald Nordland, William Seitz, Alma Thomas, and Donald Wall.
  Series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Correspondents with more than two letters are filed in individual folders by name, with the remainder of correspondence filed in a general alphabetical file. Where drafts of outgoing letters were found with related incoming letters, they have been kept together, but most drafts of letters by Gene Davis, and some original letters sent to his wife Florence, are filed under his name. Correspondents may be filed under either corporate or personal name, and cross-references are provided in the folder listing where possible. Additional correspondence with museums and galleries is found in series 4, Business and Estate Records, in the gallery files, museum files, legal records, and estate of Gene Davis files.
  - A, 1967-1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Leslie Ahlander, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    See also John and Mable Ringling Museum of Art
  - Albany Institute of history and Art, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lawrence Alloway, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mario Amaya, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - American Institute of Architects Foundation, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - André Emmerich Gallery, 1961-1977 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Architecture Magazine, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Archives of American Art, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Art in America, 1967-1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Art-in-Architecture Program, General Services Administration, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Art in Embassies Program, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - ArtForum, 1966-1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - ARTnews, 1966-1979 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Artpark, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Atelier Chapman Kelley, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Arthur Auerbach, 1965-1983 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Axiom Gallery, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - B, 1961-1985 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Gene Baro, 1966-1982 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Baltimore Museum of Art, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Michael Berger, 1971-1976 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Deeda Blair, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Murray Bring, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Brooklyn Museum of Art, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    See also Museum Files in series 4, Business and Estate Records
  - Byron Burford, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - C, 1960-1985 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Includes a sympathy letter from the Coalition of Washington Artists, 1985
  - Carnegie Institute, 1961; 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Charles Cowles Gallery, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    See also Gallery Files in series 4, Business and Estate Records
  - Chase Manhattan Bank, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Chrysler Museum at Norfolk, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Alan Cohen, 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Collector's Press, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - College of William and Mary, Joseph and Margaret Muscarelle Museum of Art, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art and Corcoran School of Art, 1953-1988 (Box 1, Folder 53-54)
  - Paul Cornwall Jones (Petersburg Press), 1968-1977 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Coudert Brothers (see also Axiom Gallery), 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Cranbrook Academy of Art, 1978-1988 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Andrew Crispo (Crispo Gallery), 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - D, 1950-1985 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Includes invitation from Dupont Theater Art Gallery to first public exhibition in 1950, and letters from Claudia Demonte
  - Douglas Davis, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Oversized ilustrated letter housed in OV 19
  - Florence Coulson Davis, 1959-1965 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Gene Davis, circa 1948-1984 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Delaware Art Museum, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - John and Jean Denman, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Des Moines Art Center, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Robert M. Doty (Whitney Museum), 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Droll/Kolbert Gallery, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Dunkelman Gallery, 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - E, 1962-1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Eleanor LeMaire Associates, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Elizabeth Weiner Gallery, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    See also Master Editions
  - Emerson Gallery, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Experiments in Art and Technology, Incorporated, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - F, 1943-1987 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Federal Reserve Bank of Richmond, 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Fendrick Gallery, 1969-1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Fischbach Gallery, 1967-1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - James Fitzsimmons (Art International), 1967-1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Betty Fleming (Betty Corcoran Fleming Fine Art, Inc.), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Alfred Frankenstein, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - G, 1965-1985 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Includes letter from Attalai Gábor
  - Dorry Gates, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Gilles Gheerbrant, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Barbara Gold, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Richard Gray, 1966-1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Green Gallery (Richard Bellamy), 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Clement Greenberg, 1979; 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Gres Gallery, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - H, 1961-1985 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Contains letters from Ben Heller, HKL Ltd., and a telegram expressing condolences from Walter Hopps.
  - Harcus Krakow Gallery, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Grace Hartigan, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Henri Gallery, 1960-1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Hirschhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden, 1974-1983 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Hokin Gallery, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Joyce Homan, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Andrew Hudson, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Hubert Humphrey, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - I, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - I. Irving Feldman Galleries, 1978-1984 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - J, 1962-1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - The Jewish Museum (Kynaston McShine), 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - John and Mable Ringling Museum of Art, 1969-1982 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, 1972-1983 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Pat Jones, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Joslyn Art Museum, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - K, 1969-1984 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Contains letters from David Katzive and a typescript description of a conceptual work by Ridge Kelley
  - King Printing, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - L, 1969-1985 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Contains letters from Jack Levine, Macha Laget, Leo Castelli Gallery, Fred Lutz, and Maurice Tuchman of the Los Angeles County Museum of Art
  - James and Jane Lodge, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - M, 1968-1985 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Contains letters from Ed McGowin, Maryland Institute College of Art, McIntosh/Drysdale Gallery, Martha Jackson Gallery, John Myers, Milwaukee Art Center, and Lee Malone
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology Committee on the Visual Arts (Wayne Anderson), 1966-1981 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Master Editions, Inc., 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    See also Elizabeth Weiner
  - Medici-Berenson Gallery (Lois Cutler), 1978-1984 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Howard Mehring, circa 1963 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Vincent Melzac, 1964-1985 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Meredith Contemporary Art (Baltimore), 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Thomas Messer (Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum), 1961-1977 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1972-1983 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Joan Mondale, 1978-1983 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Museum of Modern Art (William Seitz, Dorothy Miller), 1963-1981 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - N, 1951-1985 (Box 2, Folder 61)